Guide to the György Kepes papers M1796
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 2. Photographs
  - 2.4. Miscellaneous photographs, slides, negatives
    - Miscellaneous photographs 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      47 photographs of works by Mondrian, Sesshu, El Lissitizy, Braque, Picasso, Harold Edgerton, Vasarely, Maya Deren film still, Douglas Davis videotape stIlls, etc. Includes unlabeled series of photographs depicting skyscrapers and lights by Fritz Hinkle, copy of report titled "Pattern Recognition Techniques Suggested from Psychological Correlates of a Model of the Human Visual System" by Arthur P. Ginsburg of the USAF, published in NAECON and dated 1973, along with 6 photographs of images included in report. Also includes photographs of works from the MIT Visual Design Course, tearsheet of El Lissitizy reproductions, 3 postcards from the British Museum.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      30 photographs of works by Saul Bass, Franz Kline, a Mesopotamian clay tablet, Miro, Kirchner, Braque, Kepes, Mohly-Nagy, and others. Includes 4 cutouts of reproduced typographic works.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 4 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      28 photographs of works by Marcel Breuer, Picasso, Michael A. Noll, Juan Gris, Giovanni Di Paolo, Jarusan Boghosian, Kandinsky, Herbert Bayer, Stefan Lorant, Albers, Noguchi, Rembrandt, and others. Also photos of an integrated circuit and projectiles. Includes a postcard invitation to an exhibition at the Institute of Contemporary Art Boston with a computer drawing on front and 4 museum postcards, and 1 Gestalt drawing on paper.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 5 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      62 photographs of works by Piotr Kowalski, Mondrian, Saul Bass film stills, Burgoyne Diller, William Blake, Durer, Le Corbusier, Jean Otth videotape stills, and others. Includes photographs of a Chinese ceremonial blade, typewriters, an aerial view of Earth, a Native American bowl with insect design. Also includes unsigned photograph possibly by Kepes titled "Light Tapestry" and dated 1939-1940 with attached handwritten note, and a second photograph signed by Kepes titled "Light Study of Rhytm [sic]" and dated 1949, with similar untitled and unsigned photograph.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 6 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      38 photographs of works by Nam June Paik, Oskar Kokoschka, Raffael, Harold Walter, Jason Seley, Chardin, Jean Otth, Lissitzky, Sophie Tauber-Arp, and others. Possible original photograph by Aaron Siskind. Photos from Standard Oil Company. Ansel Adams photograph of IBM computer magnetic core storage elements, and 3 postcards of the Rosetta Stone from the British Museum.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 7 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      36 photographs of works by Lissitzky, Jean Otth video still, Allan D'Arcangelo, Giocometti, Harold Cohen, Skidmore, Owings & Merrill, Heinz Gravenort, Jean Arp, Robert Mallary. Pamphlet on Harold Cohen exhibition and his computer drawings. Possible original photographs by Nathan Lerner with related handwritten note on paper, by Fritz Heinkle (?), by G. Kepes (photogram signed and dated 1946), by Hein Gravenhorst, and by Philip Thiel. Exhibition invitation to George Rickey at Staempfli Gallery dated 1967. 2 Gestalt drawings on paper. Photographs from Standard Oil Company.
    - Description of x-ray photograph of the solar corona, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Description of first x-ray photograph of the solar corona taken from Skylab on May 28, 1973; photograph not included.
    - Environmental Forms (Box 7, Folders 4-6)
      115 photographs of works by Hans Haacke, Isamu Noguchi, Nam June Paik, Lila Katzen, Geny Dignac, and others.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 1/2 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      54 photographs. Includes images of works by Stan Vanderbeek and Moholy-Nagy; photographs of Parque Guell in Barcelona; many photographs by Nishan Bichajian for the Center for Advanced Visual Study, MIT; and others by Ugo Mulas and by August Fry. 1 scientific image of diamond minerals and two unidentified color photographs.
      Mostly 8x10 b/w glossy silver gelatin prints; some smaller formats; 2 8x10 color photographs.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 2/2 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      61 photographs. Includes images of Virgin and St. John sculpture by Van der Weyden, of a "prototype of prefab electric transformer" dated 1969, of work by Simon Nicholson, of works by Erwin Hauer dated through 1960s to 1968, and of work by Stan Vanderbeek; photographs of Parque Guell in Barcelona; many photographs by Nishan Bichajian for the Center for Advanced Visual Study, MIT; one photograph stamped "Charles Eames."
      Mostly 8x10 b/w glossy silver gelatin prints; some smaller formats.
    - Diagrams 1/2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      20 photographs and 2 paper collage constructions. Photographs by James Lee Byars, Carlotta M. Corpron, and Hua Li; of a painting by Victor Vasarely, Most photographs of contrast and visual diagrams and related paper cutout constructions. Possible photograms by G. Kepes.
      Mostly 8x10 b/w glossy silver gelatin prints; some smaller formats; works on paper.
    - Diagrams 2/2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      26 photographs and 3 acetate collage of moire patterns and 1 line drawing on tracing paper. Photographs from General Electric, by Gordon N Converse, James H. Brown, and Masayuki Nagare, and of works by Michael Gelick (signed by Kepes?) and by Fritz Glarner. 1 electron microscope image and 1 photograph of student work by D. Jesson at MIT. Many photographs of contrast and visual diagrams of paper cutout constructions.
      Mostly 8x10 b/w glossy silver gelatin prints; some smaller formats; acetate collages.
    - Negatives (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Mostly 3x4 negatives; slides and assorted uncut negatives in various formats.
      25 negatives in envelopes; assorted additional negatives including: 11 in envelopes, 2 slides, 2 uncut 33mm strip, 13 additional negatives, many uncut. Negatives of miscellaneous and various works; many unidentified. Also includes 1 small photograph.
    - Archeological photographs (Box 11, Folders 1-3, Box 10, Folders 5-7)
      Mostly 8x10 b/w glossy silver gelatin prints but also various smaller sizes.
      50 photographs of pottery and ceramics, archeological and architectural sites, stone carvings, masks, textiles, and other material. Includes works from the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Peabody Museum at Harvard, Seattle Art Museum, Museum of Fine Arts Boston, and many unlabeled photos. Also includes tearsheet from "Illustrated London News" dated 9/1/1923, postcard addressed to "Mr. and Mrs. Gyorgy Kepes."
    - Photographic panels (Box 12, Folder 2)
      8x10 b/w photos on panels; 1 smaller panel.
      16 photographs on panels showing Boston at different times of day, as well as city lights and a student project from M.I.T. visual design course.
    - Photographs 1972 and undated (Box 27, Folder 32)
      Photography of Leif Brush's art work Meadow Piano for an exhibition at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago in 1972 and an undated, unidentified photographic print of an abstract art work. Photograph has been torn.
    - Photographs 1965, undated (Box 30, Folder 13)
      Three photographs - one is unsigned, but is of a General Electric lamp. The other two are oceanographic photographs by Edwin S. Boatman.
    - Photo Album (Box 41, Folder 7)
      Originally in a photo album with the words "Photo Album" printed on front. Transferred to acid-free sleeves. Photos are standard-size snapshots, primarily of artworks.
    - Kepes Slides & Negatives of painting, design, etc. (Box 41, Folder 9)
      Appears to only be negatives.
    - Negatives and photos (Box 41, Folder 10)
      Originally in an unlabeled folder.
    - Elank Budapest (Box 41, Folder 11)
      One negative.
    - Gyorgy Kepes Negatives (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Strips of negatives of photos of people (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Negatives (Box 41, Folder 18)
      Originally in an unlabeled box together. Most of the negatives in cardboard mats.
    - Slides, Negatives, Prints, 1987, 1993 (Box 41, Folders 19-21)
      Originally in an unlabeled box together. Most of the negatives in cardboard mats. Slides in sleeves together were originally grouped together.
    - Photographic prints and negatives (Box 41, Folder 22)
      Originally in an envelope together.
    - Negatives and slides (Box 41, Folder 23)
    - Photos (Box 48, Folder 6)
      Photographs of people and artworks. Include varying sizes and formats. Small number of negatives. All originally in a smaller box together.
    - Scidenberg [Seidenberg?] Exhibition, 1983-10-08 (Box 48, Folder 7)
      Photographs of people and artworks. Originally in an envelope of this title.
    - Das Neue Russland photos (Box 48, Folder 8)
      Photographs of the covers of a journal entitled Das Neue Russland from 1930-1931.
    - Photos, 1965-1966, undated (Box 48, Folder 9)
      Bulk undated. Photos of artworks and installation of artworks. At least some of the photos are from a 1965-6 exhibition at Harvard entitled "Light as a Creative Medium."
    - Photos, 1939-1943 (Box 48, Folder 10)
      Photos of artworks. Originally in an envelope labeled "Kepes photo material negs prints etc" together. Only prints.
    - Photos (Box 48, Folder 11)
      Includes thumbnail photos glued to sheets of paper as well as standalone prints.
    - Photos (Box 48, Folder 14)
      Originally from an unlabeled photo album. Appears to be photos of a party celebrating a stained glass window of some sort. People and artwork.
    - Negatives (Box 48, Folder 15)
    - Negatives, 1937-1960 (Box 48, Folder 16)
      Also contains prints.
    - Negatives, 1968 (Box 48, Folder 17)
      The negatives appear to concern the Milan Triennale in 1968, Light Corridor, and Programmed Lights.
    - Negatives (Box 48, Folder 18)
    - Negatives and prints (Box 48, Folder 19)
    - Nature details (Box 48, Folder 20)
      Originally in an envelope of this title. Negatives. Envelope also reads: "Cracked Wall. Water (strobo), Stones, pebbles."
    - Photos (Box 49, Folder 1)
      Photos are of art works as well as landmarks around the world. Half the photos are large-format, and have been placed in a flat box.
    - Negative, oversize (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - Photographs (Box 53, Folder 1)
      Unknown prints and one negative for photographs.
    - PH2 (Box 59, Folder 1)
      Photographic prints. Originally in a box of this title. Larger format items.
    - Kepes portraits, 1977-1988 (Box 49, Folder 2)
      Contains "Photos + Contacts of Dad by Bela Kalman" and other photos of Kepes, his house, studio and family. Dates are approximate.
    - Photographs (Box 61, Folders 4-8)
      Photos originally in a box labeled I.1. Miscellaneous photographs.
    - Kowelski [?] Half Photos (Box 61, Folder 9)
    - Photographs (Box 61, Folders 10-11)
      Originally in an unlabeled box. Photos appear to be of artworks ranging from the 1930s to the 1970s, but the prints themselves are undated.
    - Photographs (Box 62, Folders 1-3)
      Originally in a box labeled I.1. Miscellaneous photographs.
    - Photographs (Box 62, Folder 5)
      Originally in a box entitled "Publicitly Documents." Photographic prints.
    - Photographs (Box 62, Folder 6)
      Originally in a box labeled I.-5. Photographic prints.
    - Photographs, 1973 (Box 63, Folder 1)
      Originally in a box labeled I-12. Photographic prints of artworks.
    - Photographs (Box 64, Folders 1-3)
      Originally in a box labeled both I-11 and Negatives, Paintings, Design, etc. Contains photographs of works of art.
    - Unsorted Negatives (Box 64, Folders 4-6)
      Originally in a box of this label. Also contains a few photographic prints.
    - Photos and Negatives (Box 65, Folders 1-3)
      Originally in a box labeled N9. Contains negatives, prints, and contact sheets.
    - Negatives (Box 65, Folder 4)
      Originally in a box labeled N8.
    - Kepes 1 Dev&c 3.50 (Box 65, Folder 6)
      Contains photographic prints and negatives.
    - Orig. Negs. - Valuable (Box 65, Folder 7)
      Originally in a folder of this title. Negatives.
    - Negatives (Box 65, Folder 8)
      Originally in a box labeled N4. Also contains slips of paper with nearly unintelligible writing that seems to concern details of each shot. They were scattered throughout the box in no apparent order.
    - G.K. Flash Lights (Box 65, Folder 9)
      Also labeled N3. Negatives, slides, photographic prints.
    - Slides (Box 66, Folders 1-2)
      Originally in a box labeled N2. 8x11 clear plastic slides that seem to have been painted on (paint is flaking off) with black paint. Possibly they were printed with ink, instead.
    - Negatives (Box 66, Folder 3)
      Originally in a box with this label. Also labeled N1.
    - Negatives (Box 67, Folders 4-5)
      Originally in an envelope labeled N15. Negatives, also contains three slides.
    - Photographs: Aerial Views and Interior Design (Box 86, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous photos (Box 86, Folder 6)
    - Slides (Box 87)
      Miscellaneous slides stacked in a box completely random with the occasional general description such as, but not limited to: 19th/ 20th century "Light", New Landscape, Color, Light Book, G. Kepes Paintings, etc.
    - Slides (Box 88)
    - Slides (Box 89)
    - Photographs (Box 26, Folder 9)
      Photographs of skematic diagrams of works of art.
    - Photographs of Kepes (Box 115, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, Kepes Paintings (Box 115, Folder 2-3)
    - Photographs, other artists and art (Box 115, Folder 4)
    - Kepes exhibitions (Box 115, Folder 5)
    - Kepes installations (Box 115, Folder 6)
    - Photograms, etc. (Box 115, Folder 7)
    - Loose prints, science, etc. (Box 115, Folder 8)
    - New Landscape 401-454 "Extra copies of illustrations" (Box 115, Folder 9-11)
    - Misc. prints, were rolled (Box 115, Folder 12-15)
    - Misc. prints, were rolled (Box 116, Folder 1-10)
    - New Landscape - "Discarded photos" (Box 116, Folder 11-14)
    - Misc. Photos (Box 116, Folder 15)
    - Oversize prints (Box 117, Folder 1-2)
- Series 3: Books
  - 3.1. Book correspondence, etc.
    - Various permissions invoices and cancelled checks (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous permissions (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Permissions letters from ALCOA, George Kostritsky, Charles L. Kuhn and others and regarding MIT Press edition of Language of Vision, Japanese edition of The New Landscape, and miscellaneous publications.
    - Sales Reports Invoices, 1962-1973 (Box 51, Folder 1)
      Reports from the publisher on sales of various of Kepes' books.
    - G. Berlin, Language of Vision, The New Landscape, 1957-1967 (Box 51, Folder 3)
      Correspondence relating to publication issues surrounding Language of Vision and The New Landscape.
    - Sales Reports, 1947-1973 (Box 51, Folder 4)
      Mostly sales reports on The Language of Vision and The New Landscape. Also contains a small amount of correspondence about possible legal action by Kepes against Paul Theobauld Co.
    - Correspondence related to Language of Vision & The New Landscape (Box 51, Folder 8)
      Letters among Kepes and lawyers about legal trouble with Paul Theobald & Company.
    - Paul Theobald, 1946-1957 (Box 51, Folder 12)
      Contracts and correspondence.
  - 3.2. Light book
    - Light notes, 6 folder(s) (Box 6, Folders 1-6)
      Light notes. In pen on paper; with drawings. Includes outlines for Light Book, various ideas for or about teaching exercises, notes on specific art works or buildings, and miscellaneous notes on light and the Light Book. Notes in original order but folders divide arbitrarily.
    - Light Book Notes (Box 83, Folders 1-5)
      Also completed chapters.
    - Light Book Notes, Symbolic Aspect (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Includes undated and untitled typescript and many pages of notes in pencil and in original order; many pages labeled with "intrinsic symbol." Themes include urbanism, cities, and the definition of symbol.
    - Light Book Notes 1/6, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Typescripts titled "Light and Color" and dated 11/5/64 and 11/17/64, handwritten notes on "modulation" and "light modulation," "figure - ground," "randomness," "visual fundamentals," "light," "education of vision," "light source," "light window," "lighting design," "aesthetic factors," "The new landscape," "light duration," "light + space," "light information," and various other topics related to light. Includes drawings.
    - Light Book Notes 2/6, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Typed page dated 3/29/67 on "color," handwritten notes on "light space," "light color," "light motion," "light modulation," "modelling," "Education of vision -- light environment," "sender, transmitter, receiver," "light modulation scale," "light terminology," "light science," "light general," "color of light," and various other topics related to light. Includes drawings. Includes typed Charles Bunn quotation on diamonds.
    - Light Book Notes 3/6, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Typescript titled "Light and Color" dated 12/15/64, handwritten notes on "city," "Eduction of vision standardization conventionalization of forms," "most important epistemological problems," "light + shadow," "challenge for change," "mobile light sources," "scheme," "projected light," "light space," "what color can do," and various other notes relating to light. New York Times newspaper clippings titled "Glare Is Eliminated by New Plastic Lens" and "Scientists Weigh Astronaut Mystery," and article titled "The Leonid meteors" from The Listener. Typed page on student work, M.I.T Visual Design Course. Four untitled typescripts and two miscellaneous typed pages.
    - Light Book Notes 4/6, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Partial typescript on "light messages. Handwritten notes on "stage lighting," "light optical echo," "information figure-ground," "light motion change," "geometry-fluidity," "architectural use," "figure ground role of contrast," "light + form," "surface modulation," "light information, communication," "light reflection (scale)," "figure-ground formation/information," "Rules of the Game," and other notes on light. Pamphlet on color charts, two pages of typed grant proposal or application. 1 miscellaneous typed sheet. Typed manuscript titled "LIGHT" dated 2/16/67.
    - Light Book Notes 5/6 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Handwritten notes on "color," "history of color use," "education of vision - unity of opposites," "light illlumination direction," "light technology," "light technology stage," "New light technology," "light sources," and various other notes relating to light. Typed agenda for "Vision, Brightness, and Design" seminar, 9/23-24/1953. Miscellaneous typed pages. Single page from Kepes's "The Visual Arts and the Sciences" article printed in Daedalus.
    - Light Book Notes 6/6 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Typescript on "Light and Color Tools (2)" dated 11/3/64, Handwritten notes on "light-mythology," "light modulation," "light color," "light science," 'light + shadow." Includes miscellaneous typed sheets. Letter from Mrs. Karl T. Compton and Boston Council for International Visitors, letter to Julie Kepes re: print exhibition at Wake Forest College, typed assignment for "ADVANCED VISUAL DESIGN" by J.J. Schiffer, typescript on stained glass by Robert P. Breading.
    - Light Book Text (Box 77, Folders 4-5)
      G. Kepes miscellaneous notes.
    - Light Book, Requests For Permission (Box 61, Folders 1-3)
      Photographic prints.
    - Light Book permissions (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Note: These permissions letters do not correspond to the original box label. Dated c. 1962 and c. 1967. Permissions reference a book or project called "Light Book" or "Light as a Creative Medium."
    - Light Book permissions 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Permissions for Light Book (identified also as Light as a Creative Medium). Includes correspondence with Ben F. Laposky, Gottfried Jager, the New York Times, US Department of Commerce, Jasia Reichardt, National Geographic Magazine, U.S. Weather Bureau, Andreas Feininger, Aero Service Corporation, Dan Flavin, Lucia Moholy, numerous museums and galleries, and others.
    - Light Book permissions 2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Permissions for Light Book (identified also as Light as a Creative Medium). Includes correspondence with United Press International, USIA, Jasia Reichardt, Alvar Aalto, Dan Flavin, numerous museums and galleries, and others. Also includes attached transcript of lecture given by James R. Johnson at Harvard University.
    - Light Book permissions 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Permissions for Light Book (identified also as Light as a Creative Medium). Also includes 2 photographs of Ludwig Herschfeld-Mack, CV for Pierre Cordier, and American Lighting Corporation brochure titled "The Lighting of a Great Museum" on lighting the Guggenheim Museum.
    - Light Book photographs correspondence (Box 15, Folder 8)
      2 letters regarding photographs acquired from the Envionmental Science Services Administration and from American Airlines.
    - Light Book photographs correspondence (Box 74, Folders 1-3)
      Correspondence to Kepes from various professionals.
    - Light Book photographs checklist (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - 3.3. Light Book photographs [as labeled]
    - 3D Geometric Art (Box 70, Folder 7)
      18 photographs: 16 photos of exhibition at MOMA in Amsterdam, 2 photos of Bordeaux Pyramid.
    - Allan Stone Artwork (Box 68, Folder 6)
      Photography of Allan Stone Artwork from the collection of Nelson Rockefeller: 3 pictures.
    - Ancient Pieces (Box 75, Folder 1)
      15 photographs: Neolithic Flint Dagger, Giacometti, art on tree bark, Satin piece with pattern- Japanese 18th/19th century, Amphora from Cypress, Large Pottery form Peru (Incan), 2 photos egyptian pottery, Babylonian Drawing on clay, 6 photos of ancient art.
    - Architecture (Box 68, Folder 9)
      10 Photographs of Different types Architectural design: House in Angkor Cambodia, House in Tokyo City, The Five Towers near Mexico City, 2 photos of the Rockefeller Center, Random building with palm tree, Monastery of Longovarda at the Island of Paros, cityscape of San Giminango- Italy, Rural Church near West Burke- Vermont, Church of the Virgin Alenkantra- Mykonos.
    - Architecture (Box 69, Folder 7)
      8 pictures: " The Stone Garden" and "Arrow Wheel"(x3) and "Cross Beams"- by Masayuki Nagare, Mayan Achitecture- Yucatan Peninsula, 3 undescribed.
    - Architecture (Box 70, Folders 2-4)
      15 photographs: postcard of Notre Dame Chapel, Island of Paros buildings (x2), Island of Hydros building (x3), Wooden strructure at University of Caracas, St. John's Baptistry door "Charitas" and "Aides", Rameswaram Temple (x2), Katzura Wantanabe #25, #20 and #7, Tokonoma of Nijo-Jinya, abandoned mill - Fall River Mass.; 15 Photographs: Kinetic light curtain - Boston Harbor, Charles Eames- Shadow and Window photos, 2 photos of Interior, Midtown Manhatten (early evening), potential building design, Crown-Zellerbach back office (S.F.), Yale Art Gallery, Nightscape of Boston, Photo by Otto Bayer- Day and Night shots of Gothic Church, Heidelberg- Illuminated Castle, Lower Manhatten as seen from Hotel St. George, Breman City Hall (Germany); 25 photographs: View from Americana Hotel, Cityscape - Berlin, Cityscape- Munich, View from Rhine River of Bayer Leverkusen, Berlin Cityscape, Heidelberg View from River, "12 Cones of Bagnolet"-France, Stuggart Cityscape, Dowtown Hamburg, Building in Tokyo, Bridge in Amsterdam, Times Square, 5 shots of Johnson Wax research Tower and buldings, 8 undescribed photos.
    - Architecture (Box 71, Folder 1)